<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Parasitology</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Parasitology</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/lab/lab12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/lab12/</guid>
      <description> Labs are complete for the semester. Great job, and good luck on the final!  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/lab/lab13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/lab13/</guid>
      <description> Labs are complete for the semester. Great job, and good luck on the final!  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lab 10: Tick Data Collection &#43; Vector-borne Disease Paper Discussion</title>
      <link>/lab/lab10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/lab10/</guid>
      <description>This week we&amp;rsquo;ll be identifying the ticks we got from last week&amp;rsquo;s lab (and from iNaturalist), and then will be having a discussion on Shapiro et al., 2017
Student Learning Outcomes At the end of this lab, a successful learner should be able to…
 First LO Second LO  Presentation Lab 10 Presentation
Worksheet Lab 10 Worksheet
Resources To be added</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lab 11: Unique Host-Parasite Systems!</title>
      <link>/lab/lab11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/lab11/</guid>
      <description>Student Learning Outcomes At the end of this lab, a successful learner should be able to…
 First LO Second LO  Presentation Lab 11 Presentation
Worksheet Lab 11 Worksheet
Resources To be added</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lab 1: Lab Setup/Parasite Diversity/Microscope Basics</title>
      <link>/lab/lab1_diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/lab1_diversity/</guid>
      <description>Student Learning Outcomes At the end of this lab, a successful learner should be able to…
 Describe the overall structure of the laboratory course, expectations for laboratory conduct, and how their grade is assessed Successfully demonstrate how to use a compound light microscope, including loading specimen slides, focusing at multiple magnifications, calculating total magnification, and to accurately measure the size of objects under magnification Label the basic parts of a compound microscope and be able to explain their function Define parasitism (in an ecological sense), identify major parasitic groups of interest, and outline some of the life history strategies lumped together under the term “parasite” Distinguish morphological differences separating major groups of helminth parasites across multiple life stages, and apply that knowledge to identify unknown specimens  Pre-Lab Materials Review the course syllabus before coming to lab.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lab 2: Parasite Life Histories</title>
      <link>/lab/lab2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/lab2/</guid>
      <description>Student Learning Outcomes At the end of this lab, a successful learner should be able to…
  Define common vocabulary used to describe parasite life cycles (Simple complex, tropic transmission, parasitic castrator, vector-borne).
  Describe the life histories of a few major parasites of importance to human or wildlife health (malaria, Schistosoma spp, Ascaris lumbricoides, Guinea Worm, etc.)
  Apply their knowledge of parasite life cycles to develop targeted intervention strategies, and develop methods to evaluate their performance</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lab 3: Host Range and Parasite Specificity</title>
      <link>/lab/lab3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/lab3/</guid>
      <description>Student Learning Outcomes At the end of this lab, a successful learner should be able to…
  Perform the necessary steps to begin analyzing data in the R language (open a development environment, Create a new analysis file, load in analysis packages, load data into the environment).
  Create basic linear models in R and interpret their outputs.
  Understand potential drivers of parasite richness across species</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lab 4:Immune Responses</title>
      <link>/lab/lab4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/lab4/</guid>
      <description>Student Learning Outcomes At the end of this lab, a successful learner should be able to…
 Explain how the melanization response helps insects fight different types of parasites Perform dissections of Odontotaenius beetles and recognize common macroparasites of them Analyze empirical observations of parasite burden and immune response to make conclusions about which types of parasites illicit stronger host immune responses  Pre-Lab Materials Before coming to lab this week, make sure to look over the learning objectives above, as well as the class presentation below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lab 5: Microparasites I</title>
      <link>/lab/lab5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/lab5/</guid>
      <description>Student Learning Outcomes At the end of this lab, a successful learner should be able to…
 Define a &amp;ldquo;model&amp;rdquo; and describe some of the ways disease models can help us gain insight Define and discriminate between state variables and parameters Explain how maximum likelihood approaches can be used to fit disease models Use functions from the bbmle package to fit epidemic models to real data, and then analyze resultant parameter estimates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lab 9: Tick Sampling</title>
      <link>/lab/lab9/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/lab9/</guid>
      <description>This week&amp;rsquo;s lab is a field trip! We&amp;rsquo;ll be sampling for ticks at Sesquicentennial state park. I&amp;rsquo;ve directly emailed you all with full information about times, where to meet, etc. Make sure to check it!
Aside from participating in sampling, the worksheet also asks you to read Shapiro et al., 2017 to prepare for our class discussion of it next week!
Presentation No presentation this week; we&amp;rsquo;re in the field!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Labs 6-7: Microparasites II</title>
      <link>/lab/lab6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/lab6/</guid>
      <description>Student Learning Outcomes At the end of this lab, a successful learner should be able to…
 Modify an epidemic model to include or remove compartments Draw a flow diagram to represent a compartmental model given a system of equations describing that model Given a flow diagram model, write a system of equations describing that system Explain the basic assumptions of the SIR model, and identify cases when violations of those assumptions may make it an inappropriate modeling choice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Labs 6-7: Microparasites II</title>
      <link>/lab/lab7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/lab7/</guid>
      <description>Student Learning Outcomes At the end of this lab, a successful learner should be able to…
 Modify an epidemic model to include or remove compartments Draw a flow diagram to represent a compartmental model given a system of equations describing that model Given a flow diagram model, write a system of equations describing that system Explain the basic assumptions of the SIR model, and identify cases when violations of those assumptions may make it an inappropriate modeling choice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Labs 8: Macroparasite Aggregation &#43; Host Behavioral Effects</title>
      <link>/lab/lab8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/lab8/</guid>
      <description>Student Learning Outcomes At the end of this lab, a successful learner should be able to…
Presentation Lab 8 Presentation
Worksheet Lab 8 Worksheet</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/policies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/policies/</guid>
      <description>Parasitology This document contains more information about the class and course policies. For more detailed information on course structure, click on syllabus tab above. For information on due dates, point breakdown, student resources, course expectations, etc., please see this pdf syllabus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/syllabus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/syllabus/</guid>
      <description> Syllabus    Date Module Topics Read Code Lab Homework   Week 1 home Course design, goals, introduction, and setup          MODULE 1: Parasite diversity        Week 2   Life history strategies and host-parasite coevolution       Week 3  Parasite richness, specificity, and host range       Week 4  Behavioral and immunological responses           MODULE 2: Directly-transmitted parasites        Week 5  Biology of microparasites       Week 6  Epidemics and interventions       Week 7  Parasite aggregation and burden          MODULE 3: Non-direct transmission        Week 9  Biology of macroparasites       Spring break  ---        Week 10  Vector-borne disease       Week 11  Environmentally-transmitted disease and sexually-transmitted diseases          MODULE 4: Disease across scales        Week 12  Infectious diseases in communities       Week 13  Coinfection       Week 14  Macroecology of infectious disease and networked populations       Week 15  Zoonoses, spillover, emergence, and One Health          MODULE 5: Closing thoughts        Final exam week school Final exam (May 6; 9am)         </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behavioral and immunological responses</title>
      <link>/read/behavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/behavior/</guid>
      <description>Reading  Ezenwa, V. O., Etienne, R. S., Luikart, G., Beja-Pereira, A., &amp;amp; Jolles, A. E. (2010). Hidden consequences of living in a wormy world: nematode-induced immune suppression facilitates tuberculosis invasion in African buffalo. The American Naturalist, 176(5), 613-624.
  de Roode, J. C., Lefèvre, T., &amp;amp; Hunter, M. D. (2013). Self-medication in animals. Science, 340(6129), 150-151.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biology of macroparasites</title>
      <link>/read/macroparasites/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/macroparasites/</guid>
      <description>Reading  Viney M, Cable J. Macroparasite life histories. Curr Biol. 2011 Sep 27;21(18):R767-74. doi: 10.1016/j.cub.2011.07.023. PMID: 21959167.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biology of microparasites</title>
      <link>/read/microparasites/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/microparasites/</guid>
      <description>Reading  Hopkins, S. R., Fleming-Davies, A. E., Belden, L. K., &amp;amp; Wojdak, J. M. (2020). Systematic review of modelling assumptions and empirical evidence: does parasite transmission increase nonlinearly with host density?. Methods in Ecology and Evolution, 11(4), 476-486.
   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coinfection</title>
      <link>/read/coinfection/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/coinfection/</guid>
      <description>Reading  Viney, M. E., &amp;amp; Graham, A. L. (2013). Patterns and Processes in Parasite Co-Infection.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disease</title>
      <link>/read/disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/disease/</guid>
      <description>Reading   Anderson, R. M. and May, R. M., Population biology of infectious diseases I Nature 280 (5721), 361 (1979). pdf available here
  Kilpatrick, A. M. &amp;amp; Altizer, S. (2010) Disease Ecology. Nature Education Knowledge 3(10):55
link to paper
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Environmentally-transmitted disease and sexually-transmitted diseases</title>
      <link>/read/env/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/env/</guid>
      <description>Reading  Nordvik, M. K., &amp;amp; Liljeros, F. (2006). Number of sexual encounters involving intercourse and the transmission of sexually transmitted infections. Sexually transmitted diseases, 342-349.
  Lanzas C, Davies K, Erwin and Dawson D. 2020. On modelling environmentally transmitted pathogens. Interface Focus.1020190056
 STD rates in Columbia, SC  News article on Columbia as no. 3 rank
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epidemics and interventions</title>
      <link>/read/epidemics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/epidemics/</guid>
      <description>Reading  McLean AR. Infectious Disease Modeling. Infectious Diseases. 2012 Dec 5:99–115. doi: 10.1007/978-1-4614-5719-0_5. PMCID: PMC7121366.
 Relevant video content  Introduction to modeling infectious diseases
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exam review</title>
      <link>/read/examreview/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/examreview/</guid>
      <description>Reading </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Infectious diseases in communities</title>
      <link>/read/communities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/communities/</guid>
      <description>Reading  Roche, B., Dobson, A. P., Guégan, J. F., &amp;amp; Rohani, P. (2012). Linking community and disease ecology: the impact of biodiversity on pathogen transmission. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences, 367(1604), 2807-2813.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>/read/setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/setup/</guid>
      <description>Reading None for this week.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Life history strategies and host-parasite coevolution</title>
      <link>/read/lifehistory/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/lifehistory/</guid>
      <description>Reading  General background on parasite life history
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Macroecology of infectious disease and networked populations</title>
      <link>/read/macrodisease/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/macrodisease/</guid>
      <description>Reading  Stephens, P. R., Altizer, S., Smith, K. F., Alonso Aguirre, A., Brown, J. H., Budischak, S. A., &amp;hellip; &amp;amp; Poulin, R. (2016). The macroecology of infectious diseases: A new perspective on global-scale drivers of pathogen distributions and impacts. Ecology letters, 19(9), 1159-1171.
  Dallas, T. A., Aguirre, A. A., Budischak, S., Carlson, C., Ezenwa, V., Han, B., &amp;hellip; &amp;amp; Stephens, P. R. (2018). Gauging support for macroecological patterns in helminth parasites.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 1 homework</title>
      <link>/homework/module1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/homework/module1/</guid>
      <description>Homework problems (feel free to copy and paste these over to another file and write your answers below each question)
  What are the different ways we can estimate parasite diversity?
  Clearly distinguish concepts of &amp;lsquo;diversity&amp;rsquo; from &amp;lsquo;specificity&amp;rsquo;
  What parasite group would likely have the lowest specificity, and why? In your answer, discuss parasite life history differences that are relevant to specificity.
  A botfly lays an egg inside the skin of it&amp;rsquo;s host.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 2 homework</title>
      <link>/homework/module2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/homework/module2/</guid>
      <description>Homework problems (feel free to copy and paste these over to another file and write your answers below each question)
  A new parasite is discovered infecting bess beetles in Mexico. Design an experiment to test whether the parasite exhibits frequency or density dependent transmission. This parasite is also found in Italy. How would you test for evidence of enemy release relative to other drivers of this parasite&amp;rsquo;s emergence in Mexico?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 3 homework</title>
      <link>/homework/module3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/homework/module3/</guid>
      <description>Homework problems   How are the models of vector-borne parasites different from those of directly-transmitted parasites?
  When modeling sexually-transmitted disease, we observe a large variation in resulting infection time series (x-axis is time, y-axis is number of infected hosts). There were at least two reasons for this. What were they?
  How do we incorporate information about sexual transmission into our estimates of $R_0$?
  A waterborne pathogen has been affecting a local population.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Module 4 homework</title>
      <link>/homework/module4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/homework/module4/</guid>
      <description>Discuss the $c_{ij}$ parameter in Dobson 2004 American Naturalist paper (i.e., what is it? what do i and j stand for?). For a pathogen that can transmit across host species and within a host species effectively, what does $c_{ij}$ look like?
  Describe all the main proposed mechanisms underlying the dilution effect. Using literature we went over in class and from other sources (google scholar), write 4-5 sentences about the current state of diversity-disease relationships (in your reading, look for papers discussing &amp;lsquo;additive&amp;rsquo; versus &amp;lsquo;substitutive&amp;rsquo; experimental designs and discuss those)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No Lab this Week</title>
      <link>/lab/setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/setup/</guid>
      <description> No labs this week! Our first lab will be next week (01/17/2024) in Coker Life Sciences, room 201. Before coming to lab, make sure to review the syllabus and come excited to look at some parasites!
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parasite aggregation and burden</title>
      <link>/read/aggregation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/aggregation/</guid>
      <description>Reading  Poulin, R. (2013). Explaining variability in parasite aggregation levels among host samples. Parasitology, 140(4), 541-546.
  Shaw, D. J., Grenfell, B. T., &amp;amp; Dobson, A. P. (1998). Patterns of macroparasite aggregation in wildlife host populations. Parasitology, 117(6), 597-610.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parasite richness, specificity, and host range</title>
      <link>/read/specificity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/specificity/</guid>
      <description>Reading  Poulin, R., Krasnov, B. R., &amp;amp; Mouillot, D. (2011). Host specificity in phylogenetic and geographic space. Trends in parasitology, 27(8), 355-361.
  Carlson CJ, Dallas TA, Alexander LW, Phelan AL, Phillips AJ. 2020. What would it take to describe the global diversity of parasites? Proc Biol Sci.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vector-borne disease</title>
      <link>/read/vectors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/vectors/</guid>
      <description>Reading  LaDeau, S. L., Allan, B. F., Leisnham, P. T., &amp;amp; Levy, M. Z. (2015). The ecological foundations of transmission potential and vector-borne disease in urban landscapes. Functional ecology, 29(7), 889-901.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zoonoses, spillover, emergence, and One Health</title>
      <link>/read/zoonoses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/zoonoses/</guid>
      <description>Reading  Plowright, R. K., Parrish, C. R., McCallum, H., Hudson, P. J., Ko, A. I., Graham, A. L., &amp;amp; Lloyd-Smith, J. O. (2017). Pathways to zoonotic spillover. Nature Reviews Microbiology, 15(8), 502-510.
  Cunningham, A. A., Daszak, P., &amp;amp; Wood, J. L. (2017). One Health, emerging infectious diseases and wildlife: two decades of progress?. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences, 372(1725), 20160167.
 </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
